The science and practice of enhancing
human performance for sport, play, and
life. Welcome to
Perform. I'm Dr. Andy Galpin. I'm a
professor and scientist and the
executive director of the human
performance center at Parker University.
Today I'm speaking with Jill Miller.
Jill is an expert in everything from
mobility to breath work to body work and
especially in what's called
selfmyofascial release. Now, in this
episode, you're going to learn more
about what these things actually are and
how to use them best. There are many
broad applications of these techniques
that extend beyond just pain relief and
range of motion and mobility. Jill will
talk about things like the role of the
fascia and some of the science that's
emerging and how that's regulating
everything from your digestive system to
your pain to your physical performance,
strength, and power output. And so I
know that whether you are dealing with
pain yourself, or you like yoga, you're
into body work, breath work, or anywhere
in between, you're going to find
something in this episode that you may
have not heard before, or at least you
find tremendous value in. So with that
said, please enjoy today's conversation
with Jill Miller. Jill Miller, thank you
so much for coming and chatting today.
Hey Andy, so good to see you. My
introduction to your work uh was, I
think, from Kelly Star, right? probably
15 years ago or more, Brian McKenzie.
But what really grabbed my attention
was I had dabbled a lot and and paid
attention to the world of we'll call it
yoga. Okay. And for the most part threw
it all away. I just thought like there's
just nothing here for what I'm doing. I
had gone through several experiences and
didn't really appreciate it. And then I
saw what you were doing and I like
thought this is the extraction. This is
the stuff we should have I wanted to get
out of yoga. just me personally and I
thought this this girl's nailed it.
You're all over it. So my thoughts of
you still to this day are that it is the
best parts of yoga that again for me
personally what I was looking for in
myself and clients and and the
scientific experience as well as there's
just so many other ways we can go about
self-care the physical body recovery.
There's just there's so many ways it can
get to and I've yet to see anybody put
it together better than you. So, as an
introduction, there was no question
there, but it was just letting you know
framing when I think about the reasons
why I was dying to get you in here for
this conversation. It is all that stuff.
And I have a I have literally three
pages of notes in front of me as you can
see. And I'm super excited to go into
that stuff. So, if it's okay with you, I
would love to talk a ton about all those
things um in a bunch of different areas.
I'm down for all of it. That's great.
I'm so glad that you connected with what
I was offering because I think what I um
did and do in the yoga space was very
radical and frankly heretical back when
I started teaching it. And um not a lot
of people got it. And it's really nice
to see that it did finally um find those
people that it was meant for and act as
a bridge back and forth between um
training, pain management, yoga,
self-care, and all those things. Great.
I have uh both your books. I have many
of your products. I've been to your
courses. I'm like such a Jill Miller
fan. It's ridiculous. All that to say, I
thought maybe we could just start
directly with this first idea. Okay.
When I traditionally had always thought
of foam rolling, it was just
compression. It was if your hamstring is
tight, you smash it and it gets untight.
And I don't know if the science works or
I don't care how it works, the
physiology. I just know if I smashed it
on there, like I felt a little bit
better in those moments. What is the
difference between that compression is
what I'll just keep calling it. And and
maybe that's the wrong term, but let me
know style of foam rolling versus other
options. and and maybe actually we'll
just start right there like what is the
compression stuff doing? What do we know
about it? How's it working? Is it
working? And then from there, let's
explore some of the other ideas and ways
and strategies we can actually maybe do
things better. Okay, so um foam rolling
has become the deacto term that is now
used I think in most places that refers
to self myofascial release. So
selfmofascial release as a category in
the self- treatment space or recovery
space is where you use an implement
which technically is called a stress
transfer medium. So we're talking about
rolling sticks. Uh we're talking about
foam rollers. We're talking about
different balls. Um even pokey tools
like uh just single things that have
knobs on them. So anything like that is
is a implement that is trying to
influence tissue in a variety of
different ways. These implements are
trying to mimic somebody's hands, right?
So this is something that you can do on
your own. You don't have to hire
somebody. You don't have to go out of
pocket. You can do it any time of day
you want, wherever and whenever you need
it. Um, so what are they doing? What are
these implements doing? they are
sometimes compressing tissue like you
said, they're um inducing local stretch.
So, if I just lay on a ball or lay on a
foam roller, I'm really just um putting
pressure into that local region. But
what happens if I stroke that implement
with my body weight uh either in a
reclining position or up against a wall
or in myriad other arrangements? What
happens if I take that implement and I
move it along the line of pull of a
muscle or across the line of pull of a
muscle? Or what happens if I do um a
different type of compressive rolling?
What happens if I um pivot the implement
or pivot my body so that it creates
traction and creates like a pinching
sensation? What are all those things
doing? They're they're affecting
different stretch receptors in different
ways and they're affecting different
layers of your body in different ways
from skin to deep and um one of my deep
interests is in the fascial tissues that
it annoys uh what is it doing to those
tissues? It's doing a lot of different
things. Um, so I recently wrote a
narrative review of the scientific
research on selfmyofascia release and
there are a lot of things that these
implements are doing to your body. Um,
one of the I think things that we can
almost all the systematic reviews can
agree on is it improves range of motion
very
quickly. So it's somehow dampening some
of the sympathetic feedback into your
body. So you can very quickly improve
your sit and reach test or shoulder
overhead or spinal movements or even you
know jaw movements. Just depends on what
is your target. What is your joint
target? What's your tissue target?
What's your intention? Um so that range
of motion improvement is really
exciting. Um, but some of the other
research that really excites me,
especially I know I'm on the podcast
called Perform and um, people want to
get more out of their workouts here, is
that not only is the rolling improving
this range of motion, but it's also
improving force output. It's improving
torque. And that's really helpful,
especially if you want to be able to
lift more over a range, right? So maybe
you, you know, you're you're deficient
in your overhead and you're overusing
certain muscles again and again, but
what the rolling does, it'll restore a
range of motion, plus you'll be able to
get more out of those muscle fibers.
They'll be able to pull more or push
more um depending on what it is the the
movement that you're trying to do. Um
the rolling also happens to dampen
sympathetic overflow. So the tools
happen to increase parasympathetic
reactivity. So that's really beneficial
if you're trying to calm down, you're
trying to gather your thoughts, um
you're trying to uh minimize your
anxiety. Um the balls and tools and foam
rollers. I always say the balls because
I'm a ball dealer. Uh but I have to note
that these things also happen with foam
rollers or rolling implements.
um they also improve your vascular flow.
So when the rolling implements um
interface with fascial tissues in
specific ways, your fascia releases
nitric oxide. So we get these local
improvements of vascular stretch and
nitric oxide release. Um I could go on.
There's many many other benefits to
rolling.
Today's episode is sponsored by EightLe.
Eightlee makes smart mattress covers
with cooling, heating, sleep tracking,
and more. I've personally been sleeping
on an EightLe mattress cover for years
now, and it's absolutely glorious. I
love it so much that I hate traveling
away from home because it means I can't
sleep on my EightLe Pod 4 Ultra. As
you'll hear me talk about endlessly on
this podcast, there really is nothing
you can do that makes more of an impact
on your health and performance than
getting tremendous sleep. And getting
great sleep requires having your body
temperature drop a couple of degrees at
night and that's hard to do on your own.
The eight sleep has been a gamecher for
me because I run hot at night or as my
wife calls it, I'm a furnace. If I don't
have something like an eight sleep
helping me cool down, I'll wake up in
the middle of the night overheating and
not feeling great. This is something
I've also found in many of the people
that I coach, especially those who are
really physically active. The EightLe
Pod 4 Ultra has two times more cooling
power, yet is virtually silent. And it
has highfidelity sleep tracking and even
has snoring detection that'll
automatically lift your head a few
degrees to improve air flow and stop
your snoring. If you'd like to try
eight, go to
eight.com/perform to save $350 off your
Pod 4 Ultra. Asleep currently ships to
the US, Canada, the UK, select countries
in the EU, and even Australia. Again,
that's
8.com/perform. Today's episode is also
sponsored by Momentus. Momentus makes
the highest quality supplements on the
market, period. Many of you know me and
you know that I do not trust the vast
majority of supplement companies and for
good reason. Many studies have shown
that anywhere between 10 to up to 40% of
supplements have accidental
contaminants, intentional alterations,
mislabeling, or other serious issues.
But Momentus is different. I literally
spent years vetting the company, their
products, and leadership team before
personally officially partnering with
them in 2023. Every single one of
Momentous's products is third-party
tested to ensure quality, and many are
even NSF certified for sport. Now, while
I love all of their products, the ones I
use the most, both personally and with
my clients, are what I call the big
three, and these are the omega-3 fish
oil, creatine, and newly improved whey
protein formula. These three supplements
have fantastic data supporting their
benefits. Whey protein for lean muscle
mass, omega-3s for brain health, and
creatine for both muscle and brain
support. And they have been shown to be
very safe across basically all
populations of people, young, old, men,
women, etc. Now, nobody has to use
supplements, and I hope you never feel
pressured to do so. But if you're
interested in supplements, it's
important that you get them from the
highest quality providers. You don't
want mercury in your fish oil or lead in
your whey protein or anything like that.
So that's why I stick exclusively to
Momentus. If you'd like to give Momentus
a try, go to
livemus.com/perform to get 20% off your
order. Again, that's live
momentous.com/perform to get 20% off. I
think if you were to ask most people,
massage foam roll, does it help range of
motion? You'd probably say, oh yeah, I
again I rolled in my hamstrings and I
stretched afterwards. I felt better. If
you ask them about does it reduce pain,
muscle soreness, again you would maybe
see some conflicting results, but a lot
of people say, "Yeah, like I was really
tight and sore. I'm not as sore." One of
the best ways to use the rolling is to
offset delayed onset muscle soreness. So
what they found, what Yan Wilkkey in
Germany has found is that the
inflammation of your delayed onset
muscle soreness isn't in the muscle
cells, but it's actually in the fascial
fabric surrounding the muscle. This is
called the epimeium. But what they found
is people who did rolling prior to a
workout had less of this inflammation in
that 48 hour time frame afterwards. So,
and one of the other fascia jokes that
the fascia researchers say is we
shouldn't be calling this DOMS, we
should be calling it doths because the
because the inflammation really is in
this fascial envelope. Um, and that's
also where these pain sensing neurons
are picking up on that. So, if you want
to offset your delayed onset, you can
roll afterwards. Um, you can roll the
next day, but really it's what the
research is showing it's better to roll
prior to to offset the DOMS. Yeah. Okay.
So, the data on muscle soreness
specifically is probably the most
pronounced in terms of the most studies
in this area, if we're talking all
things fascial, if we're talking all
things myofascial release, if we're
talking all things kind of this whole
area. But when you get outside of muscle
soreness then the questions start
arising like what other benefits am I
getting from again we'll just
collectively call all these things there
a lot of questions a lot of different
areas but I want to start at the very
very very top right so we know that this
compression stuff works let me start off
with a couple of misconceptions okay or
I'm not things I'm not sure on when I'm
doing a foam roll when I'm doing a
massage what is actually happening right
there am I breaking up scar tissue. Are
my fibers misaligned and I'm rolling
them back together? What is actually
happening at the tissue level? That
explains any of those other benefits
that we're going to get to way way
later. What's the mechanism here? I
think we have to start with describing
some of the elements of fascia in
general before we go into what is the
tool doing to the fascia because I think
what a lot of people may not understand
is how alive your fascia is. I mean,
your whole body is alive. There's
nothing really inert or fixed about your
body in general. And your fascial
tissues are comprised of so many
different cell types um and so many
different fibers. And even though it's
in general a slow to change tissue, it
is very active. Fascia is your seam
system. Got it.
Fascia connects everything in your body
from foot to face, cell to skin, and
everything in between. It
suspends your structures. It
interconnects them. But it's not just
seams. It's also the stitches of the
seams, but it's also not just stitches
or seams because it's not just fibrous.
It's also fluid and it's self-filled.
It is also invested with
250 million nerve endings. Wow. So your
fascial tissues are also a major
sensory organ of your body. I I didn't
realize the nervous system connection or
the actual nerve connection into fascia.
It's mindboggling.
So just wait there's more. Oh, I'm sure.
But you have your skin. Yeah. Your skin
and you have your muscle. But when we
think of these
areas again stretching and massage and
I'm in pain, my muscles are sore before
your work and before paying attention to
all the stuff in fascia. My assumption
when it was that these were muscle
problems. My muscle is sore. People
think that they've got micro damage in
their muscles after workouts. What is
this fascia stuff? So the fascia Yeah.
In in
your original model, you could say the
fascia is the in between all of it
stuff. It's the that's the seams. That's
the connection, right? That's the way
through. So, if I'm looking at like your
jean jacket right now, yes. Like the
jacket is my skin potentially. Your body
is underneath that. And the seams
literally are the things connecting the
muscle to the skin. And well, from toe
to toe to chin, right? Toe to chin,
everything within. So, so we can think
of fascia in a in a few different ways.
And there are many different uh fascia
researchers that model it in different
ways. Um, I like to think of it like a
stratda or like a lasagna. I think this
is an easy model for people to grasp.
So, you have your your skin and then
directly underneath your skin, you have
I mean, most people just think this is
your your fat your fatty layer, but it's
not. Within your fatty layer, you
actually have a continuous membrane
called the superficial fascia. And this
superficial fascia actually subdivides
your fatty layer into two different
layers. Did you know that you have
superficial atapost tissue and then you
have deep atapost tissue underneath this
this membrane? Yeah, you did. That's
great. Of course. Um, but the
superficial fascia also spawns these
really interesting poles called
retinacular cutudis. So, we have all
these little tent poles between our
skin, the superficial fascia and between
the superfascial fascia and what's below
that which is called the deep fascia.
And so these these tent poles are part
of what gives um our our fluffiness, the
buoyancy to our
shape. So underneath this these tent
poles of the superficial fascia, we have
sliding layers called loose fascia. This
is a fascial interface. And you can find
that right now. I'm covered with my jean
jacket, but you can just pinch your
forearm and you could you can actually
move this right, left, up, down. You can
even twist it. You can even pull it
away. So we have um an area called loose
fascia that's between the superficial
fascia stuff and what's known as the
deep fascia. The deep fascia is the
fascia that I think most people
recognize as fascia. And part of that is
because this is a lot of the mechanical
model of movement. Um, a lot of Tom
Myers's anatomy trains um sort of uh
pays homage to these continuities of
these gigantic collagen strips that run
from, you know, foot to face. And you
can really see these in dissection. Um,
so the deep fascial tissues, they are
surrounding our muscles, but we don't
just have one layer of deep fascia, we
have multiple layers of deep fascia that
glide upon each other. Um and then we
can get into the interior architecture
of a muscle itself. Your each muscle you
have is comprised of additional multiple
layers of fascia and these are
subdivided like each muscle cell is
surrounded by an
endomium right that's like if you have
one little orange ju you know in the
orange you have the little tiny segment
and it's surrounded by that cellulose
filament and inside it's just juice. The
same is an analog for your muscle and
its endamesial fascia. Then when you
have groups of these muscle fibers, um
you're wrapped in yet another layer
called
parramsium. But you must be able to have
movement between these
epimesial sliding filaments and the
parramsium. And then the parramium
gathers together in lots of bundles. And
then we have a we have a real muscle and
that's wrapped in even more fascia
that's called the epimesium. Um and
these epimesial bundles is what we call
a muscle. And that muscle and its
epimesia must move. It must have
differential
movement amongst the other muscles that
it's next to. And this is called glide.
We have glide between all these
different things. And so when you invest
a tool into these tissues, we're
stimulating cells called fibrolasts
which produce the collagen and elastin
environment. Uh we are stimulating cells
called fascia sites which are chiefly
responsible for keeping you slick
inside. They produce an abundant amount
of a substance called hyaluron. Um
you're also um manipulating fibers.
You're creating tension with your
compression. You're creating stretch,
tension, pull on these different fibers
that these fibroblasts are sensing. And
when the fibroblasts start to sense
activity, they will start to realign
things or tear things apart depending on
um depending on what you're trying to
do. So for
example, one of the I guess the old
myths that people kick around all the
time is is massage or self massage
breaking off scar tissue? Well, yes and
no. Scar tissue is comprised of very
very strong fibbrals of collagen type
one and it is necessary to be there to
stabilize an area that had been
breached.
The scar itself on the surface may look
bumpy and weird and a little bit ugly.
And there are some things we can do with
friction that can adapt that tissue that
can maybe soften the scar a little bit.
But the scar is necessary to act as a
permanent suture for the rest of your
life. Um, but typically what we're
seeing on the surface of the body, the
scar is really the tip of the iceberg
depending on how far down that wound was
into the body. Now, if we have a breach
that goes all the way to the bone, like
I'll use myself as an example. I had a
total hip replacement almost eight years
ago. And so, you know, they had a they
had a saw that greater trunker off and
there were many layers that were
breached. So, there's a scar path that
goes from skin all the way to deep. Even
though it was a very elegant surgery,
you're left with a scar path um
postsurgery. And ideally, you want to be
able to do movements and massage that
allow the fascial tissues to restore
glide so that the muscles can return to
their correct length tension
relationships. So, when we are
stimulating these
tissues, we're doing uh many different
categories of things. Um, one of my
personal favorite reasons to do
selfmyofascial release or to do foam
rolling is to enhance one's
propriception, to enhance one's ability
to know where they are in their own body
and be able to know how to move forward
or how to take the next step to know
where you are in
space. That propreceptive enhancement
has been shown to also have an inverse
relationship to pain perception. So when
we exaggerate or tickle these
propriceptive nerve endings like rfini
endings or pachini corp pusles or muscle
spindle or even golgi it has an
enhancement of improving our sensory
motor awareness but dampening down our
pain perception which is great because
we do we have this analgesic effect and
we have a window that we can train in in
better
coordination offsetting or at least
putting at a distance um some of these
pain signals
And that means that when we train, we
can then train in a better position and
over
time optimize our physical body so that
the pain doesn't have a place to sit in
our body. Right? So when we hopefully
part of your your your pain management
is having healthy muscles, helping
healthy strong movement patterns. Um,
and that is one way that doing the foam
rolling or self myofascia release or
self massage can be a a boon to pain
reduction. And there I got to include
all these different uh nerve endings as
well. This is actually amazing. What
you're saying is if you were to do that
prior to your workouts and this has some
sort of a pain dampening effect, you
could then train closer to that pain
ceiling but below it. Um, is this
deadening the nerves? Is this getting
them that the pain se receptors calm
down more? Like is this exactly what you
were talking about as a way for your
pain management strategy? When we're in
pain, we are not at our best in terms of
our movement coordination.
And that poor movement coordination
tends to be get even more movement
coordination and leads to accidents. And
so we can use the tools like a selfmy
fascia release tool to um essentially
have a state change physically from the
tissue but also it helps to create this
mental swipe. And the temporariness of
that is you know in in the research
right now is showing that there are a
lot of these acute changes um and that
these things can also happen in long
term but you have to do them again and
again. You can't just do it once and
hope for the best and it's all good. You
need to have a discipline about your
approach to self- rolling, foam rolling,
as well as the corrective
work. The foam rolling in and of itself
is not going to take care of everything.
You still have to change the body's
behavior around why that pain set about
in the first place, right? And so that
is the physical management that comes
along with proper exercise and whatever
other things, nutrition, sleep, all of
that. If I, and I've seen people do this
a thousand times, if I were to take a
tennis ball and put it underneath the
bottom of my foot right now, maybe a
baseball, a harder one, and I would roll
on that for two minutes, I would
probably stand up, and if I were to bend
over and touch my toes, my range of
motion would be greater. Right? This is
the fascial connection. Right? So, I've
undone some of the fascia, however you
want to think about this, in the bottom
of my foot. And since they transferred
all the way up to the back of my spine
and then or well the back of my head,
hopefully that has created uh some
change in in range of motion. How long
does that last? A few minutes, a few
hours. What do we know about the length
of a single acute session for that range
of motion? And is that range of motion,
if that's all I did, is that going to
have any chronic effect?
So, one of the things that rolling on an
an area like the foot. So, is there a
morphological change when I roll my
foot? Probably not. The research is
showing that you're probably not
actually changing the fascial tissues in
and of themselves, even though it we can
improve glide. We can improve um an a
relative glide amongst many different
tissues um even in a a pretty relatively
short period of time within 60 seconds
to two minutes. But one of the things
that the research is also saying is
probably that the one of the things the
rolling is doing is it's adjusting your
discomfort to stretch. So it's adjusting
your pain pressure threshold to stretch.
So there are these fluid changes,
there's heat changes. Um but in a way
you're inoculating yourself to the
discomfort of the forward bend. And so
that is allowing for a little bit more
movement. But there's also some of these
neural changes such as the rolling is um
enhancing parasympathetic features. So
perhaps um there is less muscle bracing
in your range of motion check
afterwards. So there are you know
there's a cascade of things that are
happening. I don't think we can only say
oh it's the fascia that's letting me get
that extra range. It's a part of it, but
I think there's a few
other things going on neurologically and
um in terms of fluid mechanics, and that
makes a ton of sense. It would be pretty
silly to think if I were to roll on a
foam roller for 2 minutes and then all
of a sudden I get up and I have a
structural change in the anatomy of my
quad. It's a miracle. That would be
pretty ridiculous to think, right? So,
how long is that typically going to
last? A few minutes? A few hours? As you
alluded to earlier, if your only
strategy is foam rolling or whatever the
case is, it's probably not correcting
it. So, what other stuff do I have to
do? What things can I tack on that give
me a higher likelihood of this being a
more permanent change? So I I haven't
seen any research that like they did the
rolling and then you know they check it
five minutes they check they check it 30
minutes and then you're like you're also
wondering well I bet that stretch at 5
minutes helped with the stretch at 15
show up at 30 minutes but then they
didn't say okay now go ahead and go to
your classes and come back in six hours
and let's recheck you. So, I haven't
seen something like that, but I I
certainly know anecdotally with the
clients that I work with, we usually are
rolling for a considerable amount of
time. We're not just doing a two-minute
roll and then hoping that our range of
motion is changed for the day. We're
doing strategies that are really trying
to affect certain conditions or certain
systems of the body or certain pain
patterns. And people will
have hours and hours if not days of
improvement after some of these very
deep and um disciplined ways of
decompressing certain areas of the body
or fluffing tissues as I like to say
offloading um compacted tissues. I want
to know what a a sample model of that
could look like. But before we do that,
I got a couple of quick questions on
this particular topic. We asked about
duration.
Uh my assumption is the harder you
press, the more pain you're in, the
better things get here, right? Let's
talk about that. That's how I that's how
I really get these things changed,
right? And I'm I'm not actually joking
because that was actually my strategy.
Thank you, Kelly. Starrat pain cave was
was my approach. And I always thought
the more pain I'm in, the more it's
solving the problem. It's causing the
release, whatever was working. So what
do we know
about the dosage that how long does it
have to be? How hard do I have to press?
More pain, less pain. Give me the quick
rub down on that part of it before we
get into these more comprehensive
strategies. Okay. So there's a few
different things to talk about. One is
tool hardness. Okay. Yep. And another is
it doesn't have to hurt to work. Oh,
damn. I am a soft tool champion. And I
will tell you right now, the soft tools
were 500 times more effective for me.
Yes. So stress transfer mediums are what
we call the tools. This is the the
mechanical term, the scientific term for
self-massage tools or self myofasial
release tools. So you have foam rollers,
you have um balls of various hardness,
you have uh roller sticks, you have
little like uh pokey things. Um and
hardness matters to your body because
you are a living being. You are an
organism that has responses.
Um, it doesn't feel good to get poked
with something that's hard unless you
can attenuate your response to that. So
that's that's a that's a that's a part
of this conversation strategy, right? So
what a hard tool will do is it will
initiate a sympathetic nervous system
response. This is called the muscle
bracing response because your body
doesn't want to be deformed by something
that might cause pain, that might cause
injury. This is a natural autonomic
protective response and this is called
the muscle bracing response. So there
was
it's just crazy to me but in the over
200 and something um published papers on
selfmofascial release there was one
paper that disclosed the hardness of the
actual implements used in the rolling.
Okay, just for perspective, you know,
foam rollers are they're dense foam.
They are they're very hard. Even though
an individual foam cell you can compress
it, when all those foams are together,
that's hard like wood. It's really hard.
A lacrosse ball is the same hardness as
a bowling ball. Did you know that? Did
not. There is no difference in the
material substrate of a bowling ball or
a lacrosse ball. It is the same thing.
The lacrosse ball is interesting though
because it's covered with this grippy um
rubber which I love. I love the rubber
of a lacrosse ball. But a lacrosse ball
has no yield. Neither does a bowling
ball. Neither does a foam roller or a
hard foam roller. These will just keep
pushing their weight into you and you
either suffer through it or you brace
against it. It causes so much
discomfort. You're like, I I'm just
fighting against my own tension. I'm not
getting anywhere here. So this one uh
Korean
paper it it was very special for two
reasons. It disclosed what's called
durometer. That's the that's the way we
measure hardness in objects. Right? So
you know wood is harder than foam. Um
gum is much softer than a tennis ball.
Right? So we have this this scale of
hardnesses um that's measured by um
measured um in what's called uh the
shore scale and you use a durometer to
to to test for indentation hardness. So
they uh this cohort used uh people with
chronic neck pain and they used a cohort
of over 60 year olds in Korea. So it's
very unusual to have a cohort of aged
people. Most research in self myofascial
release is on young people in college on
foam rollers. Most of them are rolling
their calves, spoiler alert, or their
hamstrings, Andy. Or their quads. But to
find old people with neck pain. Yep. And
then to either put them on a lacrosse
ball
or a soft inflated
ball. So what do you think happened to
the co? The ones that put themselves in
more pain got better. Right. the hard
ball folks.
Um, what they found was there was a a
thickening effect in the when they were
measuring EMG, the muscles were just in
tension. The trapezius muscles braced
against the ball. So, the the ball
couldn't even get to depth, right?
Because the body was protecting itself.
Those that used the soft ball had an
increase of uh neck range of motion and
a decrease of
pain because the ball could get in. the
ball was actually to do the therapeutic
work because they weren't fighting
against their own neurological tension.
Um, so in my book, soft is supreme in
terms of working with your nervous
system rather than working against it
and creating even more sympathetic
stress, propagating even more pain. Um,
there is uh some other research by a guy
named Leonard Bloom and Mark Driscoll.
Uh Leonid specializes in cerebral pulsy
and he works with families um to help uh
the children with cerebral pulsy to you
know improve their posture and pain. Um
and that he uses only soft implements uh
with these kids and it really helps them
to create a more spontaneous upright
posture and um have better movement
patterns. But what they did, what
Driscoll and Bloom did is they um did
some indentation hardness tests with a
lot of different substrates and they
made I think they made like a mock uh
cell not cell culture but they were able
to measure the distance of forces using
these different um tools into the
substrate. And what they found was that
the softer tools were able to reach the
furthest distance into the the body. So
that's one of the reasons why I'm a
really big fan of soft tools. They don't
have to hurt to work. And when you're
rolling and it hurts, that's a great
information for you. You know, the
rolling isn't about trying to make more
hurt. You're actually trying to get rid
of the hurt. But when you do roll into
something that does hurt, that also
should tell you either it's a protective
response or I'm
actually encountering parts of my body
that are inflamed or don't move well. I
think it's really good information, but
you want to be able to work with that
instead of um think that you can just
beat it out of you. Yeah. Well, I'm
still going to try to beat it out, but I
appreciate you and your science, Jill.
The glare. If you all just saw the glare
she just gave me. No, I don't do it. I
use I' I've learned my lesson from
there. So, yeah. And the other thing is,
you know, your own um muscular tension
or your gluey tissue from uh overuse or
overtraining. Um the glueiness coming
from increased viscosity of this
hyaluron that the fascia sites produce.
Uh this is really a hot mess inside of
there and we want to not have that
there. And so when we get that feedback
from tools, I think it's really great
information that we we may be burning
ourselves out and setting ourselves up
for an injury down the road. So I think
it is really really good feedback when
we come across those pain spots, but
then I think we need to to work in an
informed way to reduce that um at at all
costs.
Today's episode is sponsored by AG1. AG1
is a vitamin mineral drink with
probiotics, prebiotics, and adaptogens.
Initially, I was extremely skeptical of
AG1, as I am with all supplement
companies. But after months of
discussions with their lead nutrition
scientist and the general team at AG1,
I've been impressed by AG1's commitment
to sourcing the highest quality
ingredients and constantly updating
their formulas to have the right
ingredients in the optimal amounts. By
now, it is abundantly clear that the gut
microbiome plays a critical role in
everything from body composition to bone
health to mental health. And the
probiotics and prebiotics in AG1 help to
promote a healthy gut microbiome,
improve digestion, reduce food cravings,
and increase short- chain fatty acids,
which play a critical role in regulating
metabolism and immune responses. It's
for these reasons and many others that I
personally take AG1 almost every day.
Now, it's of course not a replacement
for eating whole healthy foods, but it
is a great way to make sure that you're
plugging in any gaps in your nutrition
to improve your energy, bolster your
immune system, and just generally help
promote a healthy gut. microbiome and
more. If you'd like to try AG1, you can
go to
drinkag1.com/perform to receive five
free travel packs plus a year supply of
vitamin D3 plus K2. Again, that's
drinkagg.com/perform to receive five
free travel packs plus a year supply of
vitamin D3 plus K2. Today's episode is
also sponsored by Element. Element is an
electrolyte drink mix that has an ideal
electrolyte ratio of sodium, potassium,
and magnesium, but no sugar. Hydration
is critical to performance, both
physical and mental performance.
Countless studies have shown that even a
slight degree of dehydration, even as
small as 1%, can lead to decreases in
physical output and mental performance.
We also know that electrolytes are
critical to proper hydration, which I've
been harping on for years. But you can't
do that proper hydration by only
drinking water. You need to get the
right amount of electrolytes in the
right ratios. And that's why I'm a huge
fan of Element. In fact, many of you
will probably remember that I featured
Element in my YouTube series on
optimizing hydration nearly 5 years ago.
I featured Element in these videos
because their blend of 1,000 milligs of
sodium, 200 milligs potassium, and 60
milligs of magnesium really is unique
and different than any other electrolyte
on the market. And it has great
scientific support. I use Element
constantly, particularly when I'm
sweating a lot, and I routinely make it
a part of my clients optimization
programs. If you'd like to try Element,
you can go to
drinklnt.com/perform to claim a free
Element sample pack with the purchase of
any Element drink mix. Again, that's
drinklnt.com/perform to claim a free
sample pack. I would imagine the same
logic extends to formal massage. So this
is if you're thinking about the classic
Swedish massage. Yes. And deep tissue,
right? So obviously the the normal thing
feels good. Deep tissue is great, but uh
probably the same thing for any type of
self-care. Uh any type of stretching if
you're to the point of extreme
discomfort, potentially not your best
strategy because of protective
mechanisms, locking up and stuff. So
some amount of discomfort, but not past
what, like three out of 10, four out of
10. So, I think they it's like a
therapeutic discomfort. I call it
comfortable discomfort, like tolerable
discomfort where you can still breathe.
Um, you know, you're you you don't have
involuntary overflow, meaning you're not
clenching your jaw. Um, I mean, some of
the things that we see when I'm rolling
people out in the classroom is their
eyes will freeze open. Um, their hands
will clench like they're holding onto a
gun and a purse at the same time. Um, or
you know, they'll do uh weird ticks with
their jaw and and this just means
they're in overflow. they're in
sympathetic overflow. They're not
engaging a therapeutic response and they
might also actually be frankly
dissociating from their body. So that to
me um is a really a removal of presence.
And I think you I think and this is what
I write about in body by breath. It's
really important that you are present
with your entire being while you're
doing this work so that you can um be a
conscious chooser of your own healing
and that it's not just happening to you
because you're getting lucky or you're
not bypassing it and you know sort of
splitting or dissociating in the context
of self- massage or massage. Now, I know
I have endured massages where I finally
am like, "Okay, I'm gonna leave
psychologically and I'm going to let
this person do whatever they want
because they're not listening to me or
I'm just choosing to leave, right? And
I'm just going to be a shell on the
table, which sounds like totally crazy,
but you know, we can make those choices,
too. Like, we don't always have to be
totally, you know, zen and present and
all of that. sometimes are like, I kind
of want to see what will happen if they
just maw on my vasis mediialis. Yeah.
Till I bruise. I just want to see what's
going to happen. Will that free up, you
know, this portion of my my knee? Yeah.
I would imagine then what you're saying
is if
you're if your myofascial release
strategy is check your phone, hands come
up with emails while you're cruising on
a foam roller for three minutes. What
you're trying to tell me is that's
probably not the most effective
strategy. You know what? It is an okay
strategy for the fibroblasts and the
fascia sites. Those fluids, those
fibers, they will respond to that
contact because it's just smashing
moving. Yeah. I mean, it's it's fine.
But I think if you really want to be in
control of this remodel of yourself, you
want to be aware. You want to remain
aware and pick up on both the subtle and
gross sensations that are percolating
from these different sensory neurons at
different levels within your tissues. I
think this is a really nice way to frame
it
because it's still not negative, right?
You hop on a foam roller for one minute,
but bad things didn't happen, but are
you getting the most bang for your buck?
And this allows people to level up when
they want to, right? So if you need to
check out for a few minutes on the
massage table, check out. Great. But if
you're also then trying to use this as a
strategy for many other things, there
are options. And just people knowing you
can use modalities like this to go after
bigger
problems is something a lot don't think
a lot of folks really realize. So I know
you have many examples of that. But
before we get to any of that, I really
want to dwell on double triple quadruple
tap on this compression idea. Okay.
I want you to walk me through. You said
glide earlier. This is what I said
earlier was I didn't realize you could
do it. I didn't realize self massage
could be anything besides compression.
Oh, okay. Right. So, hit me
with why am I pulling? You gave the
examples earlier of your skin. I had no
idea your skin should move, right? When
you pull it up and pop it like, okay,
great. But I didn't know it should glide
past and feel like that. I didn't know
when it got pinned down that that was
telling me anything. I didn't realize if
I grabbed the outside of my quad and I
punched the skin off there, it should
slide past
itself. Once I realized that, once I
started using your strategies and then I
started watching and looking at people
doing things like cupping, I was like,
"Oh,
there is way more to this game than just
compression." So whether this is massage
compression, self massage compression,
foam rolling, we're still talking
compression, compression, compression,
right? What's the other side of this
equation or the other two sides or
however you frame it to be? Yes. So your
your fascial tissues have the ability to
move in every direction. They're
vectorred in every possible angle all
throughout your body. So, um, just
squishing them is beneficial, but only
squishing them is leaving out the
possibility of offloading them or
tractioning them in the opposite
direction. So, um, this suction type of
thing that a cup can do is just so
amazing because it can allow a gapping
to occur from bone to skin rather than
you just pressing in from skin to bone.
And that can relieve a lot of
overcompression tension. um or possibly
you have
um some adhes adhesions or elomerations
um that uh can't be helped at a certain
vector and so doing techniques uh like I
say in the role model we do this thing
called um pin spin mobilize and this is
a term that I picked up from Kelly so
much right and so what we're doing is
we're using uh one of the soft balls or
any you can really do this with any tool
as long as it has grip and you place it
into your tissue and you you spin it,
you twist it, you wrangle the tissue
until you feel there is a tolerable
pinch. Once you have that tolerable
pinch, just think about that. That's a
vortex of tissue that's whirled into the
tool. That's a tremendous amount of
stretch. And then from there, you
attempt to move the tool or move your
body right, left, um, back, forth. And
so then that's moving that twisted knot
in a variety of different ways. When I
say knot, I don't mean like a muscle
knot. It's that the twisted um skin,
superficial fascia, loose fascia, and
possibly deep fascia at that level that
we're getting all this traction. And
then when you release that, there'll be
a ton of perfusion. Uh there'll be a a
whoosh of warmth and this sudden onset
of range of motion improvements um
that's local to that joint, you know. So
if I were uh doing that on the the rib
cage, you will have such dynamic breaths
after that.
Um so the pin spin immobilize that
includes this uh vector called shear,
right? So shear is where we're getting
um basically horizontal stretch. Um but
you know cupping cupping is is an
additional uh local traction that really
stretches um skin superficial fascia all
the retinacular cutis and then can even
grip into deep fascia and create a force
vector maybe even to the perryioium. So
that's the skin the fascial skin around
the bones. Um and there are of course
nerve endings and blood vessels all the
way at depth that are being um teased in
a novel way that they're not getting
dayto-day because most of right most of
gravity is pushing us into ourselves
instead of like I mean there's a good
reason like we don't want to float off
of ourselves but just think of that that
feeling you get when I'm thinking about
my husband um when just think about when
we walk the dog and I grab him by the
scruff of his neck, you know, where that
coat hanger area is, right at the base
of the neck, the upper trapezius, and I
just traction him right in that
dowardgers hump area. He doesn't have
one, but you know what I'm talking
about. Just like I would lift a puppy by
the scruff of its skin. It feels amazing
to have stretch in that direction. We
just don't get it. Um, so I try to do
that using uh two balls in different
areas of the body to to also create that
type of of offloading traction rather
than a compression traction. Um, I think
you'd have to look into the cupping
literature to see other benefits of what
that offloading type of of stretch does.
And I haven't really looked into that.
Yeah. How do I perform
decompression by myself? And as I was
alluding to earlier, this is what
changed for me, right? I can foam roll
my back. I feel a little bit better for
5 seconds. But when I do traction, when
I do decompression,
for specifically my low back, that's the
big changes I get. And that lasts hours
hours for for me personally. It's not
the same. Other areas of my body feel
better actually with compression, with
smashing. Mhm. But certainly early is it
is always going to be traction. You
mentioned glide and slide. You talked
about twisting and for people at home
like visualize this. Literally pinch
your skin like your little brother would
pinch you and twist it and do that and
keep doing that. Move it around and then
you'll let it go and once the kind of
pain from the pinch goes away you
realize like oh my gosh that whole area
is moving better now. I would just love
a few more direct examples. How can
people do traction and decompression all
by themselves? During the pandemic, I
was in peak stress just like everybody
else. I was homeschooling a 5-year-old,
a kindergartener and a three-year-old
preschooler who had never had a computer
in front of their face in their whole
lives. And all of a sudden, their
schools were on Zoom. and we were
pivoting our company
and filming all this content and it was
so stressful. I started to have and also
I was writing a book of course about
stress regulation and I started to have
panic attacks which is not and that is
not in uh something that I'm not used
to. I definitely had panic attacks in my
life, but this was
horrible.
And I had come across just some
anatomical body part that I'd read about
before, but sometimes there sometimes a
body part, especially when it's fascial
topography, it doesn't stick the first
time, doesn't stick the second time, it
doesn't the seventh time, but finally
the eighth time, I became fascinated by
this particular area of the thoracco
lumbar apenurosis called the lateral
raft. So the thoracco lumbar ainurosis
is the the plane upon plane of flat
epimesial fascia that is the tendon of
your lats. It's the tendon of your
external abdominal obliques, your
internal abdominal obliques, your
transversus abdominis, your erector
spina. They're also layers that envelop
the soas and quadratus lumboreum. So we
have a layer cake of deep fascia on the
back called the thoracco lumbar
ainurosis. All right. And within this
there is there are these little seams
where all of the layers of the thoracco
lumbar app apenosis come together. And
these are called the lateral raf or
lateral rafé if I'm pronouncing French
correctly.
So I want to see if I can massage that
lateral rafé. And so what I did was I I
have these tools called gorgeous balls
and they're soft inflated rubber balls.
And the ball feels like a human hand.
It's very grippy and they're very gushy
these balls. And so I place them on
either side of my lower back right about
where the lateral raft is. Where is
that? Just above the pelvic bones uh
connecting to the 12th rib. So we have
this little zipper. This is where this
lateral raft is. I laid on my back and I
had these gorgeous
balls on the the girth of my low back
and my sacrum was on the floor. These
balls were on the sides of my low back,
rib cage and head was on the floor. And
I laid there and I breathed for many,
many minutes using my diaphragm as an
internal massage tool
uh to reach my way into this thoracco
lumbar ainurosis.
And I experienced a lot
of
pleasure over the many minutes that I
was there. And that pleasure was I could
feel from my sacrum to the crown of my
head, my entire spine was lengthening
while these balls were broadening me
from side to side.
When I um there's a lot more that
happened there, but when I finally took
the balls out, I could feel that my
little body I'm a little 5 foot two
girly. I took those balls out and I
swear to God, I had grown an inch. All
of my discs had
reperused. My anteriorly tilted pelvis
was no longer just passively hanging out
in anterior tilt in a reclined position.
And I know this is the experience you
had because I did this with Andy and
after he did this decompression, he's
like, "Oh, my my lumbar spine is not
extended anymore. It just feels quote
unquote neutral. It doesn't feel like
it's hypertonic in this." Um, and so I
had that same experience. And part of
that back tension that I had was all the
emotional stress of carrying this
business, of carrying this family, of
not having a way out. So there was a lot
of emotional release that went along
with this decompression because I was
just holding on to so much. Um so this
is a way that one can painlessly address
back pain. Um that can address uh
arthritis in the spine that's you know
making you hold your body in a certain
way. Um and that isn't a rub out. It's
not like a roll out. I'm not like
creating aggressive friction. This
progressive position anchors these
layers of thoracco lumbar ainerosis. And
the breath is the tool that's creating
this almost like this squeegee swipe
balloon action inside your body and
creating this progressive stretch from
bone to ligament to disc to fascial
layer to muscle uh to induce better
glide throughout the entire axis. And
then within that little capsule, that
little position um there are so many
little micro movements that one can do
to address um you know very nuanced
things as well. But also you think about
this decompression of the spine isn't
just decompressing the spine. It's also
decompressing all the visceral organs
that are are hanging out just on the
front side of your body that are also
like dealing with how they process
stress or how they're processing your
posture at all times. I think there are
many different things that are
decompressing. That is the overall
emotional feeling of release. So I heard
you say release when you were leading up
this question. That word release in the
selfmofascial release literature.
Unfortunately we have this term
selfmyofasial release although I think
foam rolling is a horrible term also.
Yes. Okay. So both I know the science
hates self myofascial release. No, but
you you feel this ephemeral uh
psychological almost spiritual sense of
something has released. Some heaviness
that I felt before or some strain that I
was preoccupied with has evaporated.
Why? I just laid on two gushy air filled
balls and I breathed. I didn't even
move. I just Nothing even hurt and
nothing hurt. And my breath was the
movement. how subtle and amazing that
is. There is I would say I don't know
probably a doubling of the literature in
mileage release in the last couple of
years. Mhm. It is really really
exploding. There was not much to I mean
I would literally think it's probably
doubled. You're right. So we're learning
more clearly. We don't have all the
answers. This is a field where we have
to lean on clinicians is my opinion
because the science is catching up.
We're getting there. But we need to have
people like you who have can simply tell
us this is what I've done and this is
the people and this is the the coaching
access um to give us more tools because
the science is is just going to be
behind us for some time. So I know that
there's distension with the term
myofascial release and you've alluded to
that earlier. It's doesn't necessarily
only mean that the myofasia themselves
are being released. So um do you know is
there a more appropriate scientific
term? Is that still kind of up for
debate or landing? Um, I think I
proposed like
myofascial. What did I propose?
Treatment or Well, I think I think
massage is actually Okay. I think that's
actually a right word. Well, we don't
have a great term. We'll acknowledge
like manipulation.
Yeah, cuz the actual result the the
release, we can't guarantee. We can
guarantee the massage part or the
manipulation. The manipulation. Exactly.
Massage manipulation.
I described how I came a lot of a lot of
how I came about the rollouts that I do
are so many of them are about stress
regulation but they happen to help be so
helpful for people with pain and and so
many other different um syndromes but I
wanted to point out about this spinal
decompression um
exercise what's so notable by the way
it's I call it the lumbar hammock for
short but in in Body by breath it's
called spinal decompression via the
lateral raft. It's really an
embarrassment. I can't believe I
overtitled that, but it's just a lumbar
hammock. You're just setting up a
hammock. Um, but there is a
researcher in a professor in Wisconsin
who is forming some cohorts right now in
the firefighter community. She's had an
end of one. She has a a firefighter that
she's been working with who has been
doing these uh these these type of
rollouts, very gentle, non-p
painful, not aggressive rolling. And she
was really having trouble with a stress
test that they regularly have to go
through, I guess, to maintain their
certification. They have to run um run
up stairs with a heavy pack, many many
many flights of stairs. And she kept
breaking down. and she was having
difficulty in her preparation for the
test. And the professor said, "Give me a
month. Let me let me work with you on
some stress relieving techniques." And
she shared this and a number of other
the body by breath techniques. And she
was able to run the test with energy to
spare and with no pain. And so now she's
creating a cohort of firefighters to
test out some things. Um but the same
researcher has also been doing this work
in a much older population uh in a
population of folks with Parkinson's
disease and all of them say they have
immediate postural improvements. Their
tremors stop or diminish greatly. So
there are a lot of other autonomic
nervous system benefits that this type
of work does that isn't just necessarily
tissue dependent, right? But there are
other shifts I think that are happening
throughout the body that are notable and
can be very helpful and you know low to
no cost if you don't have balls like I'm
describing. What I've done as a
substitute is I've rolled up yoga mats.
I mean most people can find yoga mats or
something. Yeah. But the grip is
important. So you need to find something
to put over the towel that's going to
create the grip um for you. So you have
to experiment in your house. I like um
like uh you know cano bottle openers
that you use to open a mayonnaise jar.
Those are good. You have to have a few
of those. You can put those on some
rolled up towels. But the grip is really
important again because we're talking
about this layer cake. We're talking
about trying to create um horizontal
forces, sheer forces that are going from
skin all the way to bone. And but we're
not just doing it with compression like
you said. We're not just pressing in.
We're trying to traction and offload. So
you have to look for that in your house.
Quick question. Do you have any sample
videos online if someone want to see
that the exercise something like that
that we can link to the show notes? Yes,
I have many on Instagram. I have many
free videos on YouTube and I have this I
think I have a 9minute version on
YouTube of this one. Okay, great. So you
guys want to go try that out, we can
link all that directly in the show
notes. Today's episode is sponsored by
David. David makes protein bars unlike
any I have ever encountered. They have
an amazing 28 gram of protein, only 150
calories, and zero gram of sugar. That's
right, 28 gram of protein, and 75% of
its calories come from that protein.
This is 50% higher than the next closest
protein bar. Honestly, it's the best
tasting protein bar I've had by a mile.
While I often talk about the importance
of getting one gram of protein per pound
of body weight for things like muscle
health and recovery and the promotion of
lean body mass and satiety, the reality
is that for most people, getting that
one gram of protein per pound of body
weight is really challenging. However,
David makes that easy. Their bars taste
incredible and are each packed with 28 g
of protein. I eat one almost every day
and always have two or three in my
backpack when I'm traveling. like
literally always. It probably sounds
funny, but I eat them as dessert all the
time. When you try them, you'll know
exactly what I mean. The macronutrients,
one more time, are 28 grams of protein,
150 calories, and zero grams of sugar.
If you're interested in trying these
bars for yourself, you can go to
davidproin.com/perform. Again, that's
davidproin.com/perform. You alluded to
this earlier. You spoke about the
diaphragm.
I want to go to this side of the
equation. Can we start by walking us
through the two primary diaphragms we're
going to be worried about here? People
hear diaphragm, they forget there like
multiple, four of them. Top one, bottom
one. What are they doing here? And
what's this got to do with our
conversation? And you can see again the
point I'm working to here is like how do
we actually use the gut
very physiologically and
anatomically to get pain gone from
everywhere else in my body? It's so
cool. I had to write a 480 page book
about it. I love the diaphragm. Sure. Oh
my goodness. The respiratory diaphragm
specifically. Yes. The respiratory
diaphragm. The respiratory diaphragm.
Yeah. This is this interesting
horizontal muscle, this sort of
misshapen parachute. Um inside of the
rib cage, you have this um partition
between the abdominal organs and your
heart and lungs. And this muscle acts as
a a pump for both the the viscera below
it as well as the lungs and the heart
above it. Um, and it's also keeping
those things separate. If you didn't
have your diaphragm, your small
intestine would be coming out of your
nose most unattractive and disgusting.
So, it's it's there for for that reason.
The the
diaphragm, let me just uh rewind just a
little bit. When you're doing that
decompression exercise, one of the cues,
one of the attention cues that I gave to
you and to the other folks here at the
perform podcast was to once the balls
were in place was to deliberately
breathe south of the rib cage, right? to
breathe in a
gutward direction, to breathe the energy
of your attention into the balls that
are on either side of your low back. Um,
and what that enables is you to begin to
sense the actual excursion, the downward
movement of your diaphragm on Exactly
what I felt. Yep. And then it's
relaxation on exhale. This was a
basically a slow forced inhale meaning
you're deliberately inhaling and then I
asked them to not force the exhale. So
the exhale was just a what we call
passive recoil in the diaphragm space or
rather in the uh fascia space. So we
have this inhalation where you're
feeling the movement of the diaphragm
into the right and left ball. Um, but
what I also asked them, especially Andy,
to pay attention to was, I wonder if you
feel any difference in the movement on
the right side versus the left as you're
here
breathing. And was there a difference
for you? Yeah, it was I think I
described it as it was so different. It
didn't even feel like the same body
parts. It was as different as my right
knee is from my left elbow. Like it was
completely separate.
Totally different. These are two
hemispheres of one muscle. We have a
right diaphragm and we have a left
diaphragm and they're inervated
separately by a right and left frenic
nerve. Um, and your right diaphragm is a
little bit higher in your body and the
left hemisphere is a little bit lower
but can't sense it. You can't feel your
diaphragm. This partition is devoid of
muscle spindles. So, you can't really
ever know. Like I can say to you right
now, Andy, can you tell me the degree of
contraction in your right bicep? Or can
you tell me about you can tell me about
the position of your elbow by thinking
about your right bicep? But if I told
you right now, if I asked you right now,
where is your diaphragm? Yeah. Only
because I know where it is when we do
different parts of breathing, I would
know that. But I have no kinesthetic or
propriceptive awareness at all of my
diaphragm. you have no prop
propreceptive awareness of this muscle.
Um, thank God because if you had to feel
it 20,000 times a day, descending and
ascending, you'd go mad. You can't
afford that. This is this breathing is
happening um automatically for you most
of the time unless you're taking control
of it. This is a skeletal muscle and we
can control it. It's amazing. we can do
things with the skeletal muscle um that
directly impact every system of the
body. The diaphragm is a node that
spawns
responses all over our body. Um but for
me, one of the most um practical things
that I do with my clients regarding the
diaphragm is inducing pressures into all
the tissues that connect to the
diaphragm so that they can build a
better mapping of it. And at the same
time they can release tissues that
unbeknownst to them are inhibiting the
diaphragm from its full range of motion
or from its potential range of motion.
Now I will say one more thing the
diaphragm you you do feel the diaphragm
in one
particular activity and that is when it
goes into spasm and that's the hiccups.
Mhm. So that's really the one time when
you like feel the diaphragm. Other than
that, it's really hard to feel. So we
have to make it visible through
pressure, through um uh novel breathing
strategies with pressure. When I talk
about pressure, I'm talking about using
the especially the cordis ball or the
different uh therapy balls that I use in
different ways um and trying to enlarge
your propreceptive and interosceptive
awareness of the relationship of
breathing to the diaphragm. And so one
of the key places we go, there's a lot
of key places, but one of them is below
the diaphragm. will go into the gut
because the diaphragm is sewn into the
same exact fascial fabric as the
transverse abdominis. And so um if your
transversus abdominis uh is uh very
rigid from
overtraining or from sucking your
stomach in, these are things that will
create adaptations in the collagen
network of your fascia and create a lot
of of stiffness and your your diaphragm
as it descends.
There should be a corresponding
ballooning of everything that's below
it. Right? So, as your diaphragm presses
down, this is called intraabdominal
pressure. Your your organs are going to
be they're going to bob down because
they're being pressed from above by the
diaphragm. Your pelvic floor will have a
stretch. And there'll be a
circumferential stretch. The abdomen
will stretch forward. the waist and that
thoracco lumbar appinosis that I was
trying to get you guys to perceive
should also have a corresponding
distension. There's your horizontal
movement right there. That's right. But
most people are missing this horizontal
movement um because of just the way life
creates so much tension in our back
body. Um low back pain is the most
prevalent cause of pain worldwide. And
I'm here to solve that problem. I wish.
Um, so by going into the transverse
abdominis with the cordis ball, um, by
the way, if you've never gone into the
gut to massage, I don't advise going
into the gut to massage. I always advise
a sideline position first to attenuate
your pain pressure response because when
that ball or when that object goes into
the
abdomen, we go back to this muscle
bracing response. Yeah. Your
body will do anything to get to the next
breath. And if your transversus
abdominis is compromised by pressure,
your brain is going to start to signal
pain. And that's going to get you off of
the the object. It's going to be so
uncomfortable. So, we have to figure out
stealth ways to acclimate your body to
this uncomfortable pressure that is
threatening the diaphragm's movement.
So, there's a lot of paradoxes in here.
So we in in body by breath one of the
things we do is we work with mindset. So
we'll actually self-suggest things to
ourselves in order to welcome this
discomfort um in a tolerable way like I
I'm a student of my breath. Right? So we
might say something to ourselves like
I'm a student of my breath or my breath
is welcome here. You know things like
that can be really helpful because you
want to be a student of this
relationship of the diaphragm to the
transverse abdominis. And by the way,
it's not just a transversus. There's
other stuff to there, too. But, um, you
know, visceral pain is also very real.
When you put an object, you know, right
into your Yeah. into your small
intestine or your large intestine for
the first time or your bladder. Uh,
there might be some kickback. Yeah.
Yeah. Fair enough. Duly noted. Uh, I I
went for gut smash first for the record.
Of course you did. Okay. Fairness. It's
an easy story to tell. If uh my
diaphragm isn't working, I could see how
this could reduce performance, right? I
could reduce my endurance because I'm
not breathing correctly. I could see all
the things. My question is past that.
Mhm. How do I know? How can I tell if my
diaphragm is working or not? I can't
feel it like you said earlier. Maybe my
back doesn't hurt. So, I don't have any
sign of dysfunction. How is one to know
if their diaphragm is working correctly?
I believe you. It is the It is the
center of human movement. It's all those
things. How do I know? Yeah, Andrew has
a quote, "Never skip diaphragm day." I
don't know if he made it up or I It's I
have it in my book. I think it's
hilarious. Okay. Um the
diaphragm is probably working if you're
alive. Okay, fair. Your diaphragm is
working. Yep. It's doing its thing. But
your
intercostals may not be rhythmically
moving very well. You may have
inappropriate stiffness in this
relationship between the transverse
abdominis and the diaphragm. Um you may
not be getting good riers or you may be
over breathing by using what we call
accessory breathing muscles. In body by
breath I break breathing into three
different zones of breathing. There's
zone one which is this area that we've
been talking about this very relaxing
gut expansion diaphragm descending. Zone
two is the area of the intercostals
uh in combination with the diaphragm. So
we have uh rib upward rotation, rib
downward rotation. And this is you know
you have 12 sets of ribs on one side and
12 sets of ribs on the other. And
they've got to be moving well. Um, but
if you are a person who is under a lot
of stress and diabolical stress,
eventually if you're only doing rib
breathing all the time, which is a over
time, this is a sympathetic breathing
style, you'll probably end up defaulting
into what I call zone three breathing.
And that zone 3 breathing is face, neck,
shoulder type of breath where
you're you really gasping for air. And
you can see this in um asthmatics. You
can see this in, you know, sudden onset
of panic. Um but this is also not always
necessarily a harmful breath. You'll
have this type of zone 3 breath in an
orgasm, like a really heightened sense
of delight, you know, so you'll hear
these airfilled type of breath that are
very very shallow, but it's not a
long-term strategy for health, right? So
I what the way we test for it is um
through uh responses to touch in these
different areas. So I think that you
know neck and shoulder pain uh are very
common. Um and I think with the use of
tech it's gotten you know worse and
worse and worse because you have the the
hand to eye positioning that comes from
holding cell phones. So we can create we
can be in the cast of a zone 3 breather
more often than probably our ancestors
because of our um our close environment
with work and with tech. Um, and so
these tensions in the face, neck, jaw,
eyes, shoulders, um, all the way through
the brachial plexus down into hands and
fingers, um, I think are providing
more sort of a simulation of zone 3
armoring that is really unnecessary for
um, efficient length tension in zones
one, two, and three. How would I know if
I'm in one, two, or three? What would be
signs, symptoms? help me figure that one
out. Oh, chronic neck pain, jaw pain, um
headaches, that would be somebody uh or
hand pain, right? So, anything that is
coming from this, you know, all the the
areas that I described. So, this would
be uh we would be addressing that in
zone three. What do we do for that?
Well, typically I'll do some zone 2 work
first because you don't really get your
shoulders to sit on top of your rib cage
well unless your rib cage is able to
upwardly and downwardly rotate well. So,
um I'll do a lot of sideline positions
um on the cortis balls on the on the rib
cage and I'll train people to use the
ball as an elastic bio feedback. So,
they'll they'll do breathing in side
lying also in front lying. So they'll
they'll place the the ball on their
sternum um with their body weight and
feel the intrathoracic pressures
changing as they breathe into the tool.
And so you start to pick up on the
movements of breathing. Um and these
sensing of the movements of breathing
helps anchor you into more and more
appropriate long-term healthy breathing
patterns, which is zone one, zone two is
really where you want to be most of the
time. And you want to use zone 3 in case
of emergency. You're trying to cross the
finish line, by all means, like breathe
however you need to breathe. Breathe
however you're going to breathe, right?
So we need zone 3 to be filled. But if
it's always armored, if it's always in
this high stress position, you can see
right we're on camera. If you're
looking, I've got my shoulders pinned up
into my ears and my my head is being
thrust forward. U my upper back is
rounded. You know, I've got nowhere to
go.
Boxism, chronic headaches. I would
imagine this would be the same story,
right? Pretty, you can't go as far as to
say that's always because you're
breathing that way, but I would imagine
there's some pretty reasonable
correlation between somebody who is in
zone three breathing as you're
mentioning and again chronic headaches,
migraines, bxism, jaw glitching, the
whole thing, right? Even a apnea, sleep
apnneas, right? So, this nighttime um
unconscious um um mouth, jaw, tongue
behavior that is deadly. And so, what
you're really trying to do is to get
them to be more self-aware by spending
more time in two one and two. You're
saying you'll realize you're in three
and you don't even know it. Yeah. Yeah.
So, I call this playing your wind
instrument. So by becoming aware of the
feedback of the soft tissues in these
different zones uh you can really make
choices about I mean obviously your
physiology is your physiology. I live in
LA. We had fires in LA. I couldn't
believe what happened um to me
psychologically when this
this devastation was going on. So doing
um practices that familiarize you with
your own zone 1, zone 2, zone 3, and
that you have ways to at least flip the
stress switches now and again um
and bone up on practices that build your
recovery resilience or at least uh fill
up your parasympathetic cup rather than
continue to overload the sympathetic
cup. Uh I think this is this is what I'm
referring to in terms of playing your
wind instrument. But for me pressure is
always a part of that because that is
what's giving you the bio feedback about
which zone is my home like where am I
mostly breathing into? Could you give me
a one sample of what something like that
would look like? I'm laying there on my
side. How many breaths am I taking? How
long am I staying there for? Am I doing
this every day? multiple times a day. I
know the answer is, you know, depends
and all the situation, but what would
be, you know, kind of a sample strategy
here. This can change within two
minutes. Yeah. Yeah. And you want to do
the other side. Obviously, you want to
do both sides. Um, but, uh, I like to do
a lot of contract, relax type of
exercise there because that also plays
with some of the barerrow receptors in
the aorta. And so we get a really
interesting I think veagal veagal rush
from doing some of these breath hold
contract. Let me describe that to you.
So so you're laying on your side and I
have many videos on Instagram that cover
this. And um you can put like a block or
a pillow underneath your head and you
have a soft gushy ball like gorgeous or
something else underneath your ribs and
you take a dynamic breath a zone 2
breath that really broadens the rib cage
like Popey. You hold your breath and
then you stiffen. You activate those
muscles that moved your ribs apart and
then you
exhale and let go. So you can exhale
passively and just let it all
go. Um, but you can also build on the
exhale strategy and try to void your
lungs of air. So, let's say we
inhale, hold,
contract, and then
exhale, and then once you think you're
empty, then blow out four more candles
on the birthday cake. Blow out six more
candles on the birthday cake till you
get to such a absence of intrathoracic
pressure that you have a spontaneous um
inhalation. So, there's lots of
different tricks to work on creating
this elasticity of the rib cage. And I
do find that doing both ends, this
dynamic inhale hold and then the exhale
with the, you know, really forcing the
air out, forcing the air out, not in a
way where you're um pinching your face
and scrunching your eyebrows and going
into a zone 3 reactivity, but truly
using the intercostals and the diaphragm
and the transversus abdominis to get the
air out. Um, this is a really great way
to build that just the costal recoil.
And when you do that, you do the both
sides, you're this really helps the
costal vertebral joints also. So, you're
going to find that your thoracic spine,
your whole spine is going to have better
mobility, especially um rotation, like
transverse plane rotation. It's it's
amazing what it does. So, I'd imagine
once a day to start to get that going
and see what happens, right? And you
could probably get better. Once a day.
Do you want me to prescribe? Everybody
get down a little bit every day. Oh, it
makes such a difference. Morning or
night would be better. Um, I like if I'm
going to only do it once a day, I'll
Boy, that's a really hard call. You got
one, Jill. Give me one. Do I got to do
it? Let's say I'm dealing with headaches
and jaw pain at night. Rox, yeah, you
got to do this in the morning. Well,
okay. Okay. Excuse me.
You need to do it at night and the
morning. Okay. Okay. You're not going to
just let me get away with No, you're
not. No, because uh one of the things
pre-bed
uh and I've seen this happen in my
students um
doing many of these parasympathetic
exercise. So all the by the way all
these exercises that I'm describing are
going
to do what I call turn on your off
switch. They will accelerate a
parasympathetic dominant state. um and
again keep pushing off this weird
sympathetic overflow. So when people
have the jaw grinding happening at
night, they get incredibly um incredible
soreness in the all the muscles of the
face. Um a lot of this is uh you know
beyond your control. This is just
happening unconsciously. Um but what I
have seen in students that do a number
of these exercises also exercises for
the face, neck and head, not just a
cordous ball in the rib cage, but we
need to address the temporal mandibular
joint, the temporales muscle, um other
um muscles that are floating in the the
superficial fascial layer of the face.
This is very interesting. Um can help to
adjust that sympathetic switch. By the
way, these muscles of the face that I'm
describing, they also share source
nuclei in the the brain stem with the
vagus nerve. And so this is another way
to just stimulate the vagus from a
palpation point of view combined with
this breathing type of exercise that
also is pushing the gas on your off
switch. So, I think the more you can
dose up on a parasympathetic stimuli
prior to bed, um you may find over time
that you have less and less of this
unconscious clenching overnight. But I
would say if you know you have pain in
the morning every day and you want to go
work out, just do a little bit of the
work and then it'll free up so much of
your range of motion and change the pain
as we described. You know, we talked
about earlier. So, why not do a little
bit in the morning and do a little bit
at night? Yeah, it makes sense, right?
Get into good positions before you go
train and then getting into good
positions before you go to bed. Like,
how could you not do that? When we think
about stress, autonomic nervous system,
all right, we have our our two branches.
We we'll keep it as two for now, right?
So, we have our sympathetic nervous
system, fight and flight. We have our
parasympathetic rest and digest. There's
more to the story here, friends. Yes,
I'm aware, but for the sake of
conversation, we'll keep it right there.
Most people assume if I'm not at a high
heart rate, if I'm not mentally stressed
right now, that my central nervous or my
my sympathetic nervous system, my fight
or flight is not on. But there's a very
clear difference between not being on
and actively pressing the gas or turning
what do you say turning off on more?
Turn on the off switch. Turning on the
off switch. How should we think about
this? What are strategies we can do to
be more effective at turning the off
switch on more? Did I capture that
correctly? Yes. Yes.
So, one of my goals with writing Body by
Breath was trying to sell this notion
of parasympathetic
tolerance. I think that we are we're not
in a parasympathetic dominant society.
We're not parasympathetic dominant
beings. We're sympathetic dominant
beings. Um, but without doing without
investing in our own recovery,
um, it's hard to keep producing. It's
hard to stay creative. It's hard to keep
thinking clearly. It's hard to make
decisions for your family. Um, it's hard
to pick out which freaking color curtain
you want to have in your in your new
office. So it really is important to be
able to um
create the physiological ability to
allow
parasympathetic virtues to arise within
your body. So I call this
parasympathetic tolerance capacity and
um I personally need it for my own
well-being. Otherwise I just I mean I
will just grind it out. Like I will just
go non-stop. Um I think that's just part
of my
own family lineage. Like you just you go
go you produce you produce you produce.
So um and I think that um one of the
things that I've also picked up from the
fascia research space is that when we
are constantly in a sympathetic aroused
state exposed to shots of our own
adrenaline and cortisol
constantly there are adaptive changes in
our fascial tissues because of it. So
namely your um fibroblasts it's been
shown when they are exposed to
adrenaline um don't have an immediate
change but uh after 24 hours the
fibroblasts they convert due to the
presence of something called TGF beta
they start to convert into like a
gremlin version of a fibroblast which is
a myophiroblast and a
myophiroblast becomes comes a
contractile cell within the the fascial
network. And these myofibrolasts
actually have meiosin in them and they
are prevalent in people who have uh
thickened fascia, non-gliding fascia.
This was first found in thoracco lumbar
apparosis. It was first found in people
with low back pain. This high prevalence
of these myophibro blasts and um but it
doesn't happen immediately. So you can
you you can be startled and then you can
calm down and get on but these repeated
insults. So the presence of adrenaline
um over a course of 24 hours this uh the
fibroblast will start to uptake um TGF
beta and this will convert into this
myophibroblast but what happens with
that is it starts to shrink the tissue
and it's at a very slow rate. So you
don't all of a sudden become tight um
like I said in a day, a day and a half,
but over the course of a month um you
will have 1 cm of tensioning in these
tissues. So exposing yourself to
stresses is very important for
adaptation and for health. But the
chronic soaking in a stress response
will change the nature of your
connective tissue and you will have
tissue thickening. and this can lead to
pain problems. So, exposing oneself to
parasympathetic practices as a way to
offset um and refill your cup, so to
speak, I think is a really great way
to consciously balance our life because
there there's never not going to be
enormous amounts of stress showing up in
our life. Um but having this as a respit
that's within you like this is your own
internal medicine chest. In body by
breath I talk about um the five Ps of
the parasympathetic nervous system.
There's really five Ps that this is a
self-produced recipe that will change
state guaranteed every time. So the
first P is perspective. And so this is
that that mindset piece. There's a
top-down appreciation that you are
willing to create conscious change or
conscious awareness. So that top down is
a is a host for the experience. So if
you just go into rolling willy-nilly,
will it do something? Yes.
But if you're really trying to, I think,
improve your parasympathetic tolerance,
you want to be there to receive the
information that your body is going to
start to share with you. Because one of
the things that happens when you turn on
your off switch is quite frequently in
the off switch, your emotions arise. And
those emotions can be pretty unpleasant
and intolerable. And it's but it's very
important because that's what's in the
way of for many of us of communication
of growth of relational uh relational
safety all those things.
So perspective um for example, one of
the perspectives
that that I worked with when I released
the book is all of me is welcome
here because releasing a book and you
know because you've written books you
are that's my entire brain that's my my
everything I feel think and perceive is
like in that book and so it's really
scary
to you know what if this word is wrong
what if I got this theory you know what
if I misappropriated something or you
know it's so all of me is welcome here
and that really helped me with uh a lot
of the public speaking that I did post
that book but something
more simple than anybody can do is like
I embody my body I love that one because
it's just like
Okay, I embody my body. And so it allows
you to be a student of this internal
process. Parasympathetic dominant state
is not a loud state. It's very quiet. So
you really have to put yourself into a
state of deep listening and sensing in
order to
um to have it
manifest. So perspective. The second P
is place. And
place ideally for true quietude, for
true parasympathetic arousal, um you
need to have a place where you feel
safe. And that could be, you know,
indoors or outdoors, but it should be
relatively quiet. Ideally, for the
relaxation response to occur, it should
be on the darker side. So, not in the
presence of bright lights, not in the
presence of a lot of noise like
clanging, kettle bells, you know, and
things being slammed here and there. Um,
but when we work with teachers, we we
tell them how to set up environments
where they're able to establish place
for their students so that their
students feel like they can let their
guard down, right? Because you can do
this stuff in a gym. You can um you can
also do it in a war zone. We have people
working in refugee camps doing this type
of work. So it's just about setting up
parameters of like here's our space to
let go to be able to be vulnerable. So
your perspective, you have place. The
third
is
position. And
position can change your physiology
immediately. As soon as you recline,
there's just no more postural stress on
your heart and your diaphragm and you're
able to not have as much sympathetic
tone in your body. So, we always
encourage people to typically to recline
or to even boost that by going into a
gentle slope position, which takes
advantage of the barceptor reflex. So,
if we can put people in a position where
their pelvis is just a little bit higher
than their heart, higher than their
head, right, in a little bit of a gentle
slope, um that'll really enhance a
veagal dominant state. So, you've got
and also just getting on the ground
feels so good. And of course, there's
all this research about earthing and
whatnot. So, go with gravity,
perspective, place,
position. Four, pace of breath.
pace of breath or pneumatic pacing if we
want to have two P's there. Um breath
pacing exercises can alter your your
state and I'm sure you've talked about
this on your podcast but slow deep
breathing is primal um you know uh the
HHP foundation I know you are aware of
the health and uh human performance
foundation which um is a great
amalgamator of all breath research and
it's free and available online. and
Tanya Bentley is their founder and Brian
McKenzie is also one of the co-founders.
So they recently put out a systematic
review on all the breath research that
was targeted towards anxiety reduction
and what they found in you know running
all the the numbers on the on the
different papers is that slow deep
breathing was for five minutes daily is
really the the sweet spot. uh you can do
a mix of fast-paced breathing with slow
breathing, but you mustn't only do fast
breathing. Fast breathing alone is not
going to alter your stress response. You
must include the slow pace breathing. Uh
so I really appreciated this um this
paper from them because it certainly
validated, you know, my instincts and
and what I've seen in my clients.
So, um, extended exhales tend to be
really beneficial, but you can also do
extended inhales. Just make your
breathing slow paced. And I would add to
that, let's also not um use our zone 3
muscles for that breathing. So, I mean,
obviously slow breathing is going to be
involving zone one, zone two. And then
the fifth P is palpation. And we've been
talking about this palpation via
selfmyofascial release um you know the
whole time that we've been talking um as
a way to dampen sympathetic outflow and
to enhance uh sensory feedback both
propreceptive and subtle sensing
interosceptive feedback into the body
and this all enhancing the relaxation
response or this parasympathetic
dominant state. So for me, this this
recipe of the five Ps um is something
that's very doable and can happen in a
very cohesive time frame of of this five
minute time frame. Um like the simplest
thing I could suggest to your listeners
is you can just get down on the ground
and put your pelvis up on something like
a corgis ball. Um because that's going
to give you traction. So that there's
the palpation piece. Um, and you're
already, you know, positioned in the
recline and you do very, very slow
breathing there. You're hopefully in a
safe place where you're doing this and
then you say to yourself, you know, my
breath is home or I embody my body. One
of those things. And there, there you
have it for five minutes. Super easy. I
really appreciate you laying that out.
That is going to be phenomenally
effective for a lot of people. I
guarantee it. The last thing I want to
draw into all this is then how does this
relate to things like the pelvic floor,
right? So we I said earlier there's
multiple diaphragms. Oh, sure. Pelvic
floor is a diaphragm, right? This is
it's just the bottom one, right? Um I
admittedly don't spend a ton of time on
pelvic floor
development, but this is a clear aspect
of it, right? So, how does the the
pelvic floor and we could certainly do
an entire discussion, many of them on
the pelvic floor, but what are the the
top hitting things as it relates to the
conversation thus far that we should be
thinking about with the diaphragmic
floor? Uh, so one of my friends, Katie
Sinclair, calls the respiratory
diaphragm the thoracic floor, which I
think is hilarious, right? Um, and the
this pelvic floor is another uh tissue
that has uh horizontal fibers like you
know crisscrossing at this bottom of the
uh bony funnel of the pelvis and the it
looks quite similar to the respiratory
diaphragm by the way like reasonably.
Yes. And it's going to have movement
that mirrors the action of the thoracic
diaphragm of the respiratory diaphragm
rather. So as the diaphragm descends and
applies pressure into the visca um and
provides this distension the
circumferential distension to the core
there should also be a little bit of
stretch in the pelvic floor. Um unless
your pelvis is a kimbo unless your
pelvis is your pelvis is rotated pretty
far out of the pressure wave of the
diaphragm. So if the the diaphragm isn't
be able to exert this rhythmical
pressure down into the pelvic floor,
it's probably going to exert it
elsewhere. And so one of the classic
shapes is you see the kind of the banana
back that rib thrust anterior tilted
pelvis. So if the diaphragm isn't
pressurizing down to create stretch in
the pelvic floor, which is very healthy
for it, it's going to pressurize forward
into the front of the abdomen into the
rectus sheath into a a strong ligament
called the len alba, which often is
breached and creates what's known as a
diiaasis recti. So these are fascial
systems upon systems. These are um
connected sheets that rely on the
correct amount of integrity in in all
layers for this great global response.
That's actually really really helpful.
People have oftenimes heard of things
like rib flaring, right? And you just
described it a little bit differently.
So imagine again your the bottom of your
ribs are opening up. Instead of the
bottom of your ribs pointing directly
down, they're pointing say at a 45
degree angle out. Therefore, when you
breathe and you're expanding that, that
pressure is now going outwards
horizontal to your body instead of
vertically, which then pushes on the
pelvic floor to get it to move
correctly. You're also then reducing
pressure posteriorly. Right? And that
matters because that's the low back
getting pinned down again. Right? Like
low back victim yet again. Right? There
you go. Right? So, it's all of this
stuff. That's why stacking is like we
we'll use that term pretty colloally.
stacking those two diaphragms on top of
each other is the optimal scenario. Yes,
they're both tilted front or back, we
can live. It's when they are offkilter
and the pressure, whether it's the
bottom one, by the way, or the top one.
So whether this is pelvic tilt causing
the problem or rib flaring or the
opposite, either way, we're in
dysfunction, which can manifest itself,
as we've been saying all day, in a
thousand different things. Yeah. I mean,
there's so many different things to
discuss here. It's like, oh, well,
you've got chronic hip pain. That's
going to move your pelvis a little bit
away from your center of mass so that
you're not putting as much weight on
that uncomfortable hip or knee or ankle
or whatever it is. But, you know, people
people are perfectly imperfect. We're
incredibly
uh adapted to our asymmetries. Um, and
that's uh for the best. Uh, but there's
probably better and better ways. And I
think this is one of the places that I
love talking to Kelly about is, you
know, looking for uh being able to
centrate joints so that they have more
options of movement because if you have
rotated off of axis so considerably that
your range of motion in a as we account
for joint by joint um then we can get
into a lot of trouble and that's where
doing you know some really good fascial
work self myofascial release um in very
specific joints in very specific ways
can um allow for a restore a restoration
of elasticity and muscle function um in
tissues that have been compromised by
position. So this is something I I mean
I love working with people to you know
tune up these little areas that have
become messed up by you know scar tissue
or positioning or injury because you see
the you see the this remodeling
happening over time. The remodeling is
the collagen network adapting to your
new normal. Yeah. What are the accepted
best practices for dealing with
diastasis recti? My friend Katie Bowman,
she wrote a book called Diastasis Recti
and she's one of my favorite movers and
thinkers in the movement movement space.
And uh her book, one of the things that
she t talks about is that dasis erecti
is a whole body issue. Mhm. It's never
just that you have this over streretch
syndrome in the abdomen, but there were
there were probably things that
um led up to your uh
body harboring more anterior pressures.
Mhm. Although if you
are carrying triplets and twins um or if
you have overtensioned your abdomen
through overtraining um this can also be
problematic when when time when the time
comes for the abdomen to stretch. So let
me backtrack a little bit.
Diasis recti is a breach of the
connective tissue link between the right
and left halves of the anterior abdomen.
So we have these deep fascial layers
that lock themselves around the rectus
abdominis, the obliques, the transverse
abdominis, and they all zip into a
common ligament called the lana alba
which um connects from the bottom of
your sternum all the way to your pubic
symphysis. And this is an incredibly uh
a lot of integrity in this system. And
this is how you get your core force
production. Um, we've got the right half
and the left half of our abdomen working
well together to stabilize our spine,
our pelvis, and do all the things, help
us to breathe. You can imagine uh
playing what's what's the game like the
doctor game where the uh the kids can go
in and try to operation, right? So, you
imagine a slit going from your sternum
all the way down. You would spllay left
and right horizontally and you would
spllay vertically, right? You would open
up in all four areas. That's exactly the
line you're talking about. Yes. If you
can imagine. And I'm basically saying
this little piece for the male audience
because I know every female listening
knows exactly what you're talking about
already. But if you think about a
six-pack and you think about the muscles
are two columns of three, right? So one
next to each other, left and right, five
and five. I mean, I've seen dissection
where you've literally got one one
rectus abdominis from soup to nuts on
one half and then the other one you had
one uh one divided by a small tendon
inscription. I've seen so many anomalies
in the rectus. So if you can't get a
six-pack, boys, it's because you got a
one and a half pack by birth. Okay.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Well, that middle
middle line between the two columns is
exactly what you're talking about. This
is a fascia. This is a connective tissue
issue. This is why we're talking about
it, right? So when that becomes spled
open, you have that effect of of the
operation. You've had a tight line. You
called it a zipper. Perfect analogy.
It's supposed to keep those two sides
connected so force can transfer and
everything else. It's not working. It's
it's damaged or whatever, however you
want to phrase that. What it really a
100% of women get a diiaasis recti
during pregnancy and that is granted by
the amount of elastin and relaxin um
that's produced um from your growing
fetus and all of the hormonal changes
that happen within you that change the
elasticity of the tissue you must
enlarge in order for the fetus to grow.
And so the accommodation we have is we
have these elastic changes in our
fascial tissues. The problem with a
diiaasis recti is in you know after
birth for some women um it can take many
many months. Um there is never a
resealing so to speak of the you know
the heat seal like as if you were a meat
a meat packer that it never gets
reinforced and there is a very wide gap
and that gap is then filled in with
superficial fascia atapost tissue and
collagen but it doesn't have the
strength or integrity um that you had
pre-birth and so um this is very
problematic for force production through
the core we're not getting transfer of
forces from right to left or from top to
bottom. We have a propriceptive deficit.
Um and you know it it is integral. I
mean I've seen these I mean you've got
it's it's a good connection between the
right and left in terms of the the fatty
layer that has filled it in but we don't
have the muscle force production in a
cooperative way. And so um these women
can have symptoms for years of back
pain, pelvic pain, incontinence,
prolapse um but you know people who are
more lax in their connective tissue tend
to be more prone to get these um
diiaasis that linger. So most will close
about 66% will end up after a year
they'll have almost no legacy of a
separation and then you have this this
this you know third of women that are
outliers. Okay. Okay. Well, that's
important to know. Again, speaking I'm
sorry to offend, but mostly to the male
side of the equation
here, a
year, not not six weeks, not not six
weeks, not 16 weeks, right? This is 2/3
by a year, which means a third still
after a year are not back, right? So,
when we go back to this discussion on
the
fibroblasts, they're a slowmoving cell.
Yeah, they are going to repair you, but
you need time and you need consistency
to allow that collagen remodeling to
occur, right? It will or it won't. I
mean, sometimes it just doesn't because
there's pathology or there's there are,
you know, maybe you have hyperlapse
tissue. Um,
but what one of the things that Katie
talks about is that the diiathesis is a
whole body thing and we really need to
address um hip, pelvis, low back and we
really need to address shoulder, rib
cage to adjust the position of the rib
cage to try to optimize consistently the
position of rib cage to pelvis and then
do exercises that um co- occur with
breathing rhythms because by the way
Your breathing is the lining of your
core. These breathing muscles are the
lining of your birthday suit. We need to
use them appropriately to try to build
correct tension over time. But it's not
something that can be rushed, but it's
definitely something that needs to be
done. I mean, you really should be doing
um these type of breathing exercises
during pregnancy as well. I mean,
hopefully.
And this is a longer story. It's a much
longer story. Sure. I do have a chapter
in body by breath that covers diiaasis
recti and also um self-massage
application for that and I will say this
is one of the warnings I have if
somebody does have a diiaasis recti is
you don't want to put a ball right in
the center of the area that is
overstretched but you want to really
think about um creating movements that
would move
the core muscles from the side to the
middle. So you think about uh creating
vectors of pressure that don't
necessarily scrub over the midline, but
they move from the side to the middle
and doing that in in a variety of
different ways with different breathing
exercises and then with tension based
exercises to try to rebuild tension on
axis. So this is not something that's
easy to describe in a podcast, but and
it's very personal because each woman um
will have a different level of stretch.
Um, you know, some people have just more
more of their right side moved away from
the midline. Maybe it's not both sides
that moved away, right? Maybe the baby
was sitting in a way because babies sit
weird in your uterus, man. They just do
weird things, you know, just sort of
jammed up against the the right side of
your abdomen with a little bottom there
for the the last two and a half months.
And it just puts so much stretch load
on, you know, the external abdominal
oblique um and the transversus. maybe
the the you know you don't have that
much gapping. Anyway, there's different
ways to measure this with fingers and
you definitely need to get y get it
checked out by a pelvic floor PT.
They're the ideal people to diagnose um
and to give input on that. But these
things are a fascia based injury.
Amazing. We could certainly do a whole
show just on Dr without question, but I
think we'll leave people right now with
saying pelvic floor physical therapist
would be the place to go. And generally
your recommendation for for this area
for people that want a program they're
dealing with right now or maybe they're
pregnant or going to become pregnant, so
on and so forth. That would be the the
broad category people to to start off
with at least, right? Yes. And I would
also if you know you're pregnant or you
want to get pregnant, I would get
diastasis the book by Katie because she
talks about exercises pre, during, and
post. They're it's an excellent book.
What you're talking about is a case of
kind of hypermobility, right? I consider
the pregnant body on the hypermobility
spectrum. And when we have pregnant
students, we treat them like a hyper
mobile client. And there are differences
in terms of rolling with a hyper mobile
body than a non- hyper mobile body. For
sure. I love working with the hyper
mobile population. And just FYI,
according to Jessica Eckle's research,
20% of people have some degree of
hypermobility. Not this is not to say
that it's pathological. It's not to say
that it's um you know, Ellers Danlos or
Marfon syndrome, but like 20% of the
population is pretty loose. So, I've
come up with a framework for rolling
with hypermobility. And one of the uh
other clinicians I follow, I love her
work. I wrote the forward to her book is
Libby Hinesley. She wrote yoga for bendy
bodies. And she's got great information
in there for um practicing if you if you
are hyper mobile. And so, I would
include the pregnant cohort in here.
Also, um number one is breath. Use a
conscious breathing practice while
you're rolling because it will tune you
into interceptive feedback. Um, it'll
also put you in touch with a calmer
nervous system. Uh, hyper mobile bodies
tend to be higher in anxiety in general
and the there are changes in brain
regions. This is the work of like I
mentioned Jessica Eckles and Hugo
Critley. You can look this up. It's so
fascinating.
Um,
so when you're rolling, if you know that
you are hyper mobile, you should stay
towards muscle bellies. So these are all
B's. We've got breath, bellies. Stay in
the belly. Don't go rolling at the
joints. Why don't we know? Why don't we
just want to roll at the joints? Because
makes sense. Bony junctions are where
dislocations happen. So that's one of
the the third B's. Avoid bony junctions
because you couldn't easily dislocate.
um because there's just less muscle
there's less muscle mass there and
you're hanging out in your joint
capsules and your ligaments there.
Regarding rolling in the bellies, the
other thing about rolling in the bellies
is a lot of times um like you were
mentioning, there will be these
hypertonic areas in people with hyper
mobility and we want to be able to
restore good length tension so they can
really get appropriate strength in
agonist antagonist relationships. And so
rolling within the muscle bellies might
help us to decouple some inappropriate
trigger points or inappropriate
hypertonic regions. So that's that's the
aim. Um the fourth B is brace. So using
contract relax
techniques. You're not always trying to
roll to the bone. You're not always
trying to get all the way at depth. So I
can do rolling that can address some of
the more superficial tissues by creating
um a little bit of muscle bracing. And
that's going to allow me to roll
superficial fascia and also to roll
loose fascia transition with the deep
fascia. So I can where normally I would
say contract relax um to amplify
parasympathetic values in most bodies
when I'm dealing with a hyper mobile
person especially let's say they have um
hypermobility in certain spinal segments
I actually want them to keep some amount
of tension in there while they're
rolling so I can get some of the
benefits some of the maybe the
parasympathetic benefits of rolling but
I don't want to lose some of my support
benefits so that's it's very
personalized there. Um and then yeah to
avoiding going all the way to depth and
again dislocating. So the bracing can be
very important staying superficial. So
this takes us back to superficial
fascia. We can reap a lot of the
parasympathetic benefits of rolling and
the propriceptive benefits of rolling.
by staying in the skin, the fatty layer
and the superficial fascia. The majority
of the sensory neurons um within the the
nerve net that's associated with the
fascial tissues, the majority of them
are in the superficial fascia. And so I
can get a lot of propriceptive bang for
my buck by staying on the surface. And
um that might be all it takes to give
the that propreceptive feedback to a
very loose person to improve their
positioning. So a lot of times and this
goes along with the contract relax also
um a lot of the time with the very hyper
mobile person they have a really hard
time sensing uh where their joint
junctions are. They blow past them which
isn't good for overall stability. I mean
they can go there and they should
occasionally but maybe not load in a
really weird vector right so working
superficially and working with the
contract relax can then heighten my
propriception of of my body um and then
I also say with hyper mobile people like
when in doubt don't roll it out you can
cause injury you don't necessarily
always know until it's a day too late
but um I do encourage people who are
hyper mobile to roll out especially if
they are the the highly anxious type or
also have digestive challenges. So you
know in
hypermobility when you think about um
super loose people super bendy people
it's not just the fascia that's
comprised of collagen but all of your
organs are comprised of collagen and
there are you know your your eyes are
comprised of collagen. There are so many
other weird symptoms that hyper mobile
people will have. Um, uh, breathing
problems, um, autoimmune challenges. A
lot of them have mass cell activation
challenges and, um, uh, IBS symptoms.
So, there's just like a host of things.
So tamping down the sympathetic
overflow, putting them into a place
where they can be reflective and calm is
I think very very helpful for for all of
that. Going to the other end of the
spectrum, somebody that needs to gain
flexibility,
needs to gain um mobility
outside of of
course, you know, the foam rolling and
things you've described so far.
Where does static stretching land in
this equation? Do you like it? Do you
hate it? Should it be done in a
particular way? Oh, I love all movement.
I love I know you do. Static stretching.
I love isometric work. Um, where does it
fall for people who are very um muscle
bound or maybe even what we would call
scar tissue bound? So, somebody who
maybe has overtrained like say they want
to have a really big bubble muscles. I
call these people where you have just a
more bicep than is necessary for you
know general health. Um but they've done
it by really overtraining. Um I think a
combination of rolling and static
stretching. What we see with the the
rolling can actually allow for that
temporary elasticity to show up. You can
actually improve joint positions after
rolling. So, I'd recommend that as a
prescriptive for them. Um, and you can
roll the bicep. You can do um techniques
called stacking where you have like the
balls like a vice on either side of the
bicep. Yeah. Um, you can also just, you
know, lean against the wall with a block
between your rib cage and your arm and
you have a ball here and you have a ball
here and you just lean and create like a
pancake of your bicep and then do
different movements of the elbow,
different movements of the shoulder and
create different vectors and that can in
increase elasticity so quickly. And then
I would work on static stretching just
to to do longheld traction within the
fascial tissues. But I would also work
on the antagonist. So that would there
would need to be some tricep work. Um
I'm just thinking about this particular
model. I mean but you also need to work
into the forearm because you've got you
know myofascial expansion into the uh
membrane between the radius and the
ulna. You know this basically is
perryostial sheath. So there's there's a
lot more to it, but um I've seen this
in many clients and they're always
shocked that after a few days of rolling
and static stretching that they gain
generalized improvements in range of
motion all over their body. Um but
they're they're really not going to do
it on their own. They need to Yeah. Some
of these people they just they just they
need to be led day after day. um and
then their mind is blown and then they
go right back to their overtraining
after that. You mentioned at the very
beginning and I and I said when I tend
to think
of manual
therapy I almost always associate this
as pain. In other words, I did too much
training in my quad. I'm going to roll
it out so I'm not so sore. Or I think
about I'm tight, right? So I'm going to
use these two things. I basically didn't
think about this area at all outside of
those two cases. Either I'm tight, so I
want to release things more. I'm my
back's bound up. I'm tight from a 12-h
hour plane flight or you you following
stuff or and I'm sore.
You just alluded to some of them now,
but what are some of the other benefits
that have been shown either
scientifically that you're aware of or
just you've seen in your clinical
practice that we can get from and we'll
just keep calling it selfmmyofascial
release or similarish things? There are
so many benefits to self myofascia
release. Um now mind you I already
mentioned I have a bias. I'm a ball
softball person. This is the evidence
from all the literature. So this is a
combination of rollers and sticks and
tools. This is not about vibrating
tools, by the way. So this is like just
really cheap implements that anybody can
do home care with. Um so it improves
movement coordination. You just gain
better propriception by rolling. Um it
improves range of motion and mobility
and that those changes can be obvious
very very quickly. um either rolling
like along the spine, you can change
your shoulders. Rolling around the knee,
you can uh rolling around the knee, you
can help your hip, you can help your
knee. So, uh it works everywhere. Uh the
surprising I think some of the
surprising thing is that the rolling
improves torque. So, when you roll, the
muscle that you're targeting will be
able to generate more forces afterwards.
Um and this is specifically with
rolling, not necessarily static
compressive. So, um, that I'm not I'm
not sure of. I don't think anybody's
done that research with torque and just,
you know, but there's a lot on actual
strength and torque in in this specific
realm. So, regardless of that other
section, who cares? We know for sure.
Uh, and it's been shown again many times
at many angles that this stuff will
enhance acute force production. That's
great. Um, it decreases pain. There you
go. That's great. Yeah. You woke up,
you're sore, get on the ball. Yep. roll
yourself out and go practice again. Um,
it reduces arterial stiffness and
improves vascular and epithelial
function. It's really good. You know, we
don't want to have sticky vascule that's
for sure. So, getting stretch um through
this um you know, pressure and uh
ringing very helpful. Um it decreases
delayed onset muscle soreness. So
whether that it times it out so that you
get it on day three instead of day two
or you just have less of that
inflammation. So that's a good thing. Um
it induces physiological relaxation and
parasympathetic features which is one of
my favorite parts about it. Yeah, of
course. It's a chill pill without taking
a pill, right? Um it reduces lympadeema
and uh decreases local tissue
inflammation. And there's some really
cool research out of Harvard. Uh Bo Reio
did some uh research with very very soft
tools. I'm talking about the amount of
pressure that a pencil eraser would
exert if you dropped it into your hand.
Um when they they destroyed some
anterior tibialis of of mice and they
did these uh very gentle oscillations
using this implement. The mouse can't do
self myofasial release. So this was
administered through these little like
little tiny vices. Um, but the it was a
very very soft latex, not a hard um
thing. So, I'm extrapolating here uh for
that because yeah, the mouse did not
roll itself. Uh, but it was a tool.
Yeah, we get it. There's some research
out of Germany. Dr. Robert Schlip is one
of my favorite fascia researchers. He's
one of the originators of the fascia
research uh congress and the fascial
research society. He has found um with
this uh group he's working with in a uh
mental health institution there that the
rolling is helpful from major depressive
disorder. Oh yeah. Um they're doing
surveys um you know very regarded
surveys you know before and after
rolling uh around affect around memory
and cognition and they're finding that
the rolling um changes some of the uh
tissue mechanics as well as um improves
their emotional affect. Um, and then
finally, it's helpful for interosception
and sustained attention. So, there's
some work um out of Canada. Um, I'm
blanking on that researcher's name.
Well, I'm sure we'll find that and
hopefully put it in the show notes for
you, but I can appreciate all this stuff
because I didn't appreciate any of that
before really coming across some of the
stuff you were doing. And I know that
the field is evolving. We're learning
more.
This is a particular area that I
actually don't care that much about the
molecular mechanisms. I'm interested in.
I think it's really cool. We do. The
fascia researchers are very interested
in it. I know. I know you are. But why
I'm saying I almost don't care is I
didn't care that this was working
because it was repairing tissue damage
inside a muscle or if this was a nervous
system or if this was a connective I I
didn't really care. What I cared about
was I don't hurt as much anymore
afterwards or I'm seeing this change. Is
this helping me get better? It's
interesting. I of course as
physiologists like to hear the the
things. We'll learn more about it. I'm
sure the field will get more specific.
You'll find different tools, different
strategies, techniques work for better
applications and outcomes and all that,
but it's incredibly valuable in my
opinion to have people like you who know
the science based on where it stands
now. We know the limitations. We know
what we don't know. We know what's been
shown to not work. But then you have on
the other side of this equation
thousands of hours, years of experience
with countless types of clientele
personally with courses with seminars
and you can really add context to saying
well we've tried this and we've seen
this and we've noticed this. So when you
have a field like this where the science
is just is where it is having that
clinical experience is incredibly
valuable. So, I can't thank you enough
for coming by today, sharing a ton of
research, a ton of physiology, lots of
personal anecdotes. I know that uh
people if they want to see direct
examples, they can go and and check out
uh all your videos and your free things
you put out there, and we'll link to all
of that, of course. So, thank you so
much for all of that and and all the
years as well, and we really appreciate
you coming by today. Thank you, Andy.
Your work has been life-changing for me
and I love being a friend of yours and I
also love being a student of the
education that you offer. Awesome. Thank
you so much. I hope you enjoyed today's
discussion with Jill Miller as much as I
did. To find direct links to the videos
we referred to earlier, Jill's courses,
seminars, products, and other services,
please check out the links provided in
the show notes. Thank you for joining
for today's episode. My goal, as always,
is to share exciting scientific insights
that help you perform at your best. If
the show resonates with you and you want
to help ensure this information remains
free and accessible to anyone in the
world, there are a few ways that you can
support. First, you can subscribe to the
show on YouTube, Spotify, and Apple. And
on Apple and Spotify, you can leave us
up to a five-star review. Subscribing
and leaving a review really does help us
a lot. Also, please check out our
sponsors. The show would not exist
without them and their exceptional
products and services. Finally, you can
share today's episode with a friend who
you think would enjoy it. If you have
any content questions or suggestions,
please put those in the comments section
on YouTube. I really do try my best to
read them all and to see what you have
to say. I use my Instagram and
ex-profiles also exclusively for
scientific communication. So, those are
great places to follow along for more
learning. My handle is Dr. Andygalpin on
both platforms. We also have an email
newsletter that distills all of our
episodes in the most actionable
takeaways. We have newsletters on how to
improve fitness in V2 max, how to build
muscle and strength, and much more. To
subscribe to the newsletter, just go to
performpodcast.com and click newsletter.
It's completely free and we do not share
your email with anybody. Thank you for
listening. And never forget, in the
famous words of Bill Bowererman, if you
have a body, you are an athlete.